welcome everyone it's a pleasure to be
here again and I'm excited to get to
some of the questions that I mean the
first thing I'd like to do though is I'd
like to thank all of my patreon for
their support and I'm getting a lot of
requests for more one-on-one time with
me I appreciate that
I would ask everybody to appreciate that
my time is getting very stretched and so
what we're going to do is we're going to
introduce two new - new peers on patreon
with limited sports one tier will allow
you a one or like email correspondence
with me the other one will allow you to
have a one-hour chat with me plus some
email correspondence with me we're going
to call that John's pen pal
tear and said so that will go that will
go up on patreon and go live right after
the q and A's is done
so again deeply appreciative of all the
support trying to be as responsible as I
can to all of you so thank you again so
I'd like to start with a question from
Carole King and she asked me question
about the marshmallow test and and how
it's been reinterpreted to represent
economic disadvantage and then what my
general thoughts are about scarcity so
so the first thing just quickly go over
the marshmallow test this was a famous
test largely around the work of idak
initial and what it consisted of was you
would put a it was under what's called
the delay of gratification framework and
what you would do is you would bring in
a small child typically around four
years four years older a little bit
older you find something they like a
marshmallow hence the name of the test
he would put a marshmallow in front of
them and then he would say you can have
the marshmallow whenever you
but the longer you would like but if you
wait and it was often the longer you
wait there's a increasing chance you'll
get a second marshmallow and so what you
were measuring is how long the children
could delay gratification how long they
would delay before they even gave in to
impulse in the first marshmallow and
then what came out of this whereas a
series of very strong predictions now
there's two kinds of predictions that
came out of this and we have to keep
them distinct the first and this is the
one that Carol is referring to has to do
with long-term predictions so there's
ability to delay gratification it was
was purported was sometimes reported as
better or at least as good as measures
of general intelligence for predicting
your future longitudinal success your
long-term success how well you're going
to do in school how well you are going
to do in your in your work life how well
you're going to do in your relationships
and so this was considered a very big
thing it was considered one of the
mainstays of the idea of emotional
intelligence is something distinct from
intelligence yeah because this ability
to delay gratification was considered
central now that's the one set of
predictions and address those these
remember there's a second and I want to
come back to those
so recently it was found in an attempt
to replicate this study with a greater
number of participants much more diverse
sampling that the ability to delay
gratification was actually being
confounded with when they did it and
they didn't find the replication the way
it was purported what they found was in
the earlier research there was a serious
confound with socioeconomic status so
what they were finding was what they
went back and did the reanalysis of the
original data but they found was
children who could delay gratification
came from higher socioeconomic status
children who couldn't delay
gratification came from a lower
socioeconomic status no here's the thing
that first all makes sense
if you have brought up in a quite
wealthy environment it's not that risky
for you to delay gratification if you
brought up in a more impoverished
environment it is very risky for you to
delay gratification so it makes sense
actually for children right in these
different socio-economic classes to be
able to delay gratification through
different degree okay that's all said
and then once you realize that the
ability to delay gratification is being
affected by socioeconomic status you
then realize that socioeconomic status
is a very powerful predictor of how kids
are going to do so the kids that delayed
longer came from higher socioeconomic
status and that higher socioeconomic
status predicts their long-term success
and therefore the idea that the delay of
gratification was independently
predicting this long-term success falls
away now that's important not just
because the marshmallow test is famous
but this ability to delay gratification
is one of the sort of central things
around meaning of versions of emotional
intelligence this is why I'm very very
suspicious of the notion of emotional
intelligence as something distinct from
general intelligence now this lines up
with a lot of increasing work around
scarcity mentality when individuals are
put into scarcity their cognition goes
through significant transformation often
in ways that can be seen from a more
long-term perspective as deleterious but
the thing you should know is that
scarcity mentality is not just in an
economic if I put you into a situation
where you feel you have time scarcity or
that you have metabolic energy scarcity
so in any way in which an important
resource that contributes to your
ability to solve your problems is
suddenly in your in your apprehension
significantly limited you will lose
cognitive flexibility you become much
more impulsive much more limited and the
alternatives are considered you will be
much more short-term
all kinds of things happen if you move
into a scarcity mentality and so part of
what's going on and like I said this is
in one sense it's very adaptive because
if you are things that are think of
things are very scarce you should focus
your limited resources on the more
problem of the more probable outcomes
the more probable outcomes the more are
the more media ones and so on and so
forth this is important in general
because there has been I think an unfair
often criticism of certain of the to put
this in because I'm questioning the
whole argument that the moral behavior
of poorer people they seem to be more
irrational Margaret Thatcher famously
made this argument a long time ago right
and and that is to miss the whole fact
that people who are socioeconomically
poorer off do face scarcity mentality
and therefore their behaviour shifts
into this more short term really
flexible less creative more reactive
response to the environment which is
adaptive and makes sense all that being
said I don't think the we should throw
out all of the research done by either
commercial because they also did a bunch
of other predictions that aren't
longitudinal and therefore are plausibly
not confounded the socioeconomic status
and this has to do with some of the
manipulations and interventions they did
so in particular and the reason why this
I think should be preserved is is
because this evidence that I'm now going
to talk about is convergent with
independent evidence so for example what
things can you do to get children
irrespective of their socioeconomic
status to be able to increase their
ability to delay gratification so now we
can talk about this differently because
we're not talking about how the children
come in from their environment we're
talking about interventions we could
give any of the participants and see how
it changes their behavior and so one of
the things that seems to be predictive
of an ability to delay gratification is
your ability to do what what I call a
transparency opacity shift this is to
step back
and look at your processing rather than
automatically looking through it this
was famously done with one a girl in the
experiment who was taught to pretend
that she was looking that there was a
frame around the marshmallow and she was
looking at a picture of a marshmallow
rather than a marshmallow and she
famously said well you can't eat a
picture so she was stepping back and
looking at her representation and
realising its distinction from the
object and that's affords the delay of
gratification and this lines up applause
ibly with how mindfulness and other self
control strategies improve our ability
to deal with our impulsivity so you know
the media sort of presents it as you
know the marshmallow testers has been
just sort of disconfirmed that's a
little like that's a little to him
fisted what we should say is instead
there's a confirm with socioeconomic
status that points us to another
important relevant variable that has
important policy implications which is
the really you know the real impact of a
scarcity mentality on our cognitive
framing on our cognitive problem-solving
but we should also remember that there
are aspects of the marshmallow
experience experiment that shouldn't be
rejected because they have to do with
attentional and cognitive strategies
that you can eat anyone can use to
intervene and increase their ability to
reduce impulsivity and almost all our
therapeutic strategies involved in these
kinds of transparency opacity shifting
dis identification strategies etc so
that's I think sort of my best take on
the status of the marshmallow test right
now so I now and I would like to turn to
a question from a patreon supporter
Sergey he asked could you speak much
more on your concept of existential
inertia and serious play it's a long so
I have a lot of an episode that has a
large chunk on that I have a whole
separate talk on there on gnosis that's
on my channel if you're interested so I
can't give that complete argument here
because of time limitations the base
idea of existential inertia is it comes
it's it's derived from Frankfurt's
notion when things are unthinkable to us
in it I think that's also nation on an
older notion by James about when options
are viable or live options to us so
Frankfurt gives the example of you know
that he has a child he couldn't simply
abandon the child now what does he mean
by that
he doesn't mean he can't imagine
abandoning his child and he can't make
derive implications about that you know
how it might reduce his monthly expenses
or whatnot he can do all of that
imaginary imaginal work but what he
can't do is in create a salience
landscape with wit and with in which he
can assume an identity a particular
agent arena relationship such that he
will start to carry out the action
of abandoning and his child so I don't
quite like the term unthinkable but
that's that's that's his term so we're
sort of stuck with it so what I
understand aim to me using the
explanation I just gave is that we can
run the propositional and Fermi
propositional also means pictorial right
where we're using pictures as images we
can run the propositions in our head but
we can't actually go through the
prospective world and participatory
transformations that are needed to do
the salience landscape create the sigil
awareness trigger the right procedural
skills and get the right agent arena
participation going such so that we will
begin to undertake the task that is
being merely represented in a
propositional option now of course you
know it's a good thing to not abandon
your children but my notion of
existential inertia is the reverse so
consider somebody who can think about
that they want to stop getting into this
they keep going into this horrible
pattern in their romantic relationships
they know it they could say I keep
this horrible pattern in my romantic
relationships they can derive inferences
in their mind about what it would be
like if they didn't have that pattern
they would suffer less they might beat
somebody better for them their
friendships wouldn't be so massively
taxed they can imagine not being in
being in a relationship that is not part
of this horrible powder they can do all
of that stuff but what they can't do
they don't know how to sculpt their
perspective all knowing there's salience
landscape so they get the situational
awareness and they do not know how to
assume and assign identities such that
they get the participatory coupling to
the world that they can move to that
place where they are a different kind of
person inhabited at a different arena
and those deleterious patterns no longer
have a purchase on them so in that sense
the place they want to get to is
unthinkable to them that's what I mean
by existential inertia and that's of
course why people go into therapy they
go into therapy because they're often
that people very rarely do not have you
know good some good propositional
knowledge of what their issue is all
right that's that's typically not the
problem in therapy it's not like that
when somebody's coming in and they're
trying to go blah blah you know I keep
repeating these cycles they can
articulate it propositioning but they do
not know how to bring about the
perspective of and participatory
transformation that's all interesting I
think but then the the issue comes up
well what's going on in therapy that
helps to alleviate that now I think
therapy is addressing both existential
inertia and existential ignorance I
won't go into the existential ignorance
right now that's the point that's but
that has to do with the fact that very
often when we're facing significant
transformation we are ignorant like the
person going into therapy we are
ignorant of what that perspective of
knowing would be like we are ignorant of
what that new identity will be like and
therefore we're we're really unsure in
it because of this deep ignorance what
we will be losing if we make the change
or what will we we will be missing if we
don't make the change so I think
to use the example more fully going to
therapy you're facing existential
inertia since I died I don't know how to
bring it about and then coupled to that
and often causally related to it is I'm
facing existential ignorance and then
what you need to do is you need to
engage in serious play so the serious
play deals with the existential
ignorance by giving you a place that is
an enacted analogy that has enough of
the features of the prospective
all-knowing and the participatory
knowing you want to enter into without
having you fully committed to it you're
not all the way there yet so let's say
you're in therapy and you're trying to
work out a complex issue you've had with
a family member you'll engage in serious
play with the therapist they may take on
the role of your family member and so
that triggers enough perspectival
knowing and participatory engagement
that you can see what it's like to
perhaps transform those but you're not
under the threat and notice how this
would make interact with the scarcity
mentality I talked about but you're not
under the threat of actually confronting
your family member so there isn't the
tremendous you know irrevocable risk and
so you you you get into this place where
you're seriously playing you're enacting
an analogy that's liminal between the
world you and the self you're trying to
leave and the world and the self you're
trying to get to and so that's what I
mean by serious play this this enacting
where I some symbolic right analogy of
the identity I want to get to of the
world I want to move to and I play in
that right that's what the enacted is I
play enough but I play in it seriously
I'm not playing in it for fun I'm
playing it because I'm trying to trigger
the prospective woman the participatory
change hopefully enough so I would get a
sense of what is needed that will help
of course alleviate the existential
ignorance what it can also help do is
give you a place with and this is how we
acquire a lot of our developmental
skills by praying
in that little place I could start to
know how to transform my perspectival
and participatory knowing and get out of
the existential inertia so I hope that
answers that question that's broadly
what I think is going on
so the patreon SIA asked me your
description of symbol sounds a lot like
a complex web of mental models objects
that get manipulated in your head
enabling you to do counterfactual
reasoning these mental models interact
with each other but also sensory inputs
so your experience of the world is
through these models would that be a
fair description and then says I have a
machine-learning background and your
description of symbols as a lens fits
very well with models and machine
learning which are statistical
distributions that you fits your data
and if they don't approximate the real
hidden distribution of observation the
model will miss important patterns in
the world um so I think yes I think but
I think that I I think we've got a genus
species thing with it we've gotta take
care of I think the way you're using
models mental models so psychologists I
have some issues with how that is used
in within psychology because it's often
used in a very nebulous unform alized
way so putting that aside but if I
understand you correctly you know I
think I do because I have familiarity
with the notions you're invoking for
machine learning I would say that models
are a much more comprehensive there
genus they have to do with a lot of the
ways in which we are forming parts of
interaction with the world I would say
that a species of what you're calling
models are symbols and they have to do a
lot of very specific functions above and
above and beyond just successfully
modeling the world to us so as I tried
to indicate you know in some of the
lectures I won't go over all of these
symbols have you know these functions of
X stasis
they have functions of invoking
participatory knowing respectable
transformation goes back to what I was
talking about serious play they they
engage us in serious play so that they
have an inherent the transformative
aspect to them that is not necessarily
the case for you know many of our mental
models and that's transformative aspect
that ability to afford self
transcendence that ability to sort of
trigger an agogic transformation the
ability to thereby mediate between
whatever frame I'm in right now and on a
frame that I'm aspiring to all of those
things like I said that there's there's
there's I unpack this in much more
greater detail in the episodes I don't
have time to do it now but what I would
say that what's specifically different
about a symbol how I'm using it which is
not the same way it's used traditionally
we'd like within machine learning where
you put for example complete compare
symbolic processing with connectionism
I'm using it how it's used within
cultural anthropology and and theology
and the related philosophical discourses
where as I said this specific difference
the centrality of the functionality of
the symbol in affording the
transformation self transcendence is
what for me a crucial specific
difference between a symbol and just a
broader class of models so I hope that
answers your question
so there's let's see I'm just checking
for the next question and just coming up
now
so this is from patron back to ogres I
enjoy the company thank you all so much
I'll lay the questionnaire in three
parts do you think meaning making
narratives are more powerful when armed
with cultural specificity I think that's
that's a very good question I'm coming
to a distinction in in the video series
that is it yet
I haven't made that explicit but well so
I'll bring it up now but I will I will
ask for your indulgence because a more
complex argument is still forthcoming
so part of what and I've already
discussed it to some degree and you've
also seen it in I think some discussions
it's you might have seen it I should say
I shouldn't
oh wow those so so presumptuous forgive
me but perhaps some of you have seen it
in some of the other video discussions
I've had with people so whereas I think
the machinery of meeting making it right
in terms of relevance realization is
universal of course how that fits to a
specific historical environmental
context is right going to be different
so let's use the analogy like the
machinery of evolution is universal but
how this particular creature is adopted
it's gonna be very different in this
environment from how this features
adapted etc so this is the idea of you
know of niche construction so what that
means I think is that there is going to
be your relevance realization machinery
is going to tailor you and fit you to a
particular cultural historical
environmental niche and therefore to
degree to which you have things that are
specific to that niche construction you
will thereby increase or enhance your
fitted nests if you'll allow me that you
cognitive fitness to that particular
environment and and what this can that
mean is that certain things become
indispensable to your sense making
capacity the example I often use is that
English because of my particular
cultural historical environmental
background the language English is
indispensable to me I could not I cannot
do without it I can't be a cognitive
agent or at least a degree that I need
to be or want to be without English I'm
either taking this away from me I can't
communicate
I can't pose or solve many other
problems that lose access to literacy
etc so English is therefore
indispensable to me and I think there
are many ways in which your relevance
realization will produce things that are
indispensable to you and therefore your
particular set of symbols might pick up
on that right cultural historical
environmental specificity and help you
to engage with those indispensible
functions they're indispensable
precisely because they give you a kind
of specific you thinking you'll kind of
let let's say a context sensitivity and
that's all I think implied by some of
the arguments and evidence I presented
the issue for me is to confuse that
indispensability with metaphysical
necessity it would be to claim that
every cognitive agent must speak English
or they cannot be a cognitive agent that
would be to claim metaphysical necessity
now of course there are things that are
metaphysically necessary for agents I
think age like agents have must have a
capacity to determine the consequences
of their own behavior they if they don't
have that they can't be agents right and
what I'm trying to get at is that many
things that are indispensable I think
for it have often historically thought
to have been metaphysically necessary so
I think that particular symbol systems
then make claims for exclusivity Ultima
si finality perfection which i think is
doesn't make any sense given the way
that relevance has no essence but I
think that that and I think that's an
important point and I'm gonna I mean the
process of making that argument in an
extended fashion in this series but I
also think that that there's often a
confound there and I sort of understand
it because if if a particular set of
symbols is indispensable to you for you
it's unthinkable in the way I just
explained a few minutes ago it's
unthinkable to you that there is a
viable other way of doing it and then
right and and that makes sense to me but
that is not the same thing as it being
transcendentally metaphysically
necessary so it would be ridiculous for
me I think you're all aware of this for
me to make the 2x2 say less unless you
speak English you're not an agent
there's no way there's no other way to
agency except through speaking English
cognitive agency you'd say that's
ridiculous there's bit right no no not
at all okay so I think what comes out of
this it's that we have to understand and
we have to therefore deeply respect
things that have a cultural specificity
for the reasons I've articulated as long
as that is reciprocated with
understanding that that cultural
specificity unless there's an
independent argument that it is
metaphysically necessary or essential to
our cognitive agency that if that kind
of argument is not forthcoming then the
person who is making use of the
culturally specific thing must
acknowledge that they should not confuse
indispensability with any kind of
metaphysical necessity so that's how I
would answer that first question so I I
think I answered your second question
because your second question is
predicated on me giving a no to the
first one and I gave a qualified yes so
I'm going to move
- I think it's not it I think that's
yeah that's it okay so I've got a
question from Alex patreon Alex well
would I'm very curious about absurdity I
had an information recently about how
things feel absurd the forces want to
deal with how real it is I'm wondering
if the reality of absurdity and horror
can be similar in a way to the reality
of an ecstatic experience and in that
could there be deep insights that could
be useful I'm having a bit of trouble
I'm having a bit of trouble sorry they
just moved articulating exactly what I'm
getting at but I appreciate if you could
elaborate a little bit Thanks that's a
really good question and I do think
there is a deep connection between your
absurdity machinery armature power
absurdity machinery because I've
experienced absurdity as well so
experiences I think this is a fair way
to say it that we could describe as
profound absurdity so I think there is a
deep connection between the machinery of
absurdity the cognitive processing of
the shirt of absurdity and that by which
we have stasis I think in fact and then
NATO also argued something similarly and
of course he's the author of the essay
the absurd did I make use of he thinks
that absurdity is as I've argued on his
behalf not driven by inference or
argumentation but actually driven by a
capacity for self transcendence it's
driven by a capacity to move to a
perspective that encompasses our
lower-order perspective and then define
that there is a clash in relevance
between the perspectives so what's
relevant in the high-order perspective
is not relevant in the lower orders
perspective and this may be the
perspective where I'm sort of living my
life now interestingly I gave a talk on
this recently it's what's on like I made
it created a link to this on my channel
if you want to give it
recently stoic on stoic on X in Toronto
about the stoic practice of the view
from above where they get you they
deliberately got you to practice that's
rising above yourself and viewing
yourself from a more encompassing
perspective not just spatially but also
temporally and socially etc and there's
all kinds of cognitive science evidence
which I go into detail in that top about
how that affords enhanced cognitive
flexibility and ability to reduce
impulsivity increase capacity for wise
reasoning because what it's doing is
it's really manipulating your
perspective you're you're taking a hey
more encompassing perspective it's
deliberately transforming your
perspective all knowing and then by
doing that right and and altering the
agent arena relationship you you create
right you create challenges to people's
sense of identity and their sense of
agency you get colorful versions of this
and what's called the overview effect
when astronauts are seeing the Earth
from space it provokes profound
experiences of awe and wonder in which
the bright lately and it has a huge
perspectival aspect to it there's
tremendous sense of beauty and it also
has a tremendous participatory
transformation they come back feeling
often that they need to transform their
lives and their identities have been
significantly altered so this is very
powerful stuff that's going on and it
can and part of what I was trying to get
out of the talk is ok it can go into
absurdity right you can produce Wonder
and awe but right if there is if the
person can't bring some kind of
connection between the two perspectives
the higher-order perspective can
undermine the salience II and the
relevancy realization and lower order
perspective but precisely because that's
I mean the fact that the higher order
perspectives can undermine the lower
perspective is what gives them their
transformational power but if that
transformational power isn't properly
constrained or limited it can just eat
away at the capacity to be connected in
your lower order perspective the
perspectives you know of your everyday
life and that can
you feeling deep absurdity so the trick
maybe that's the wrong word that sounds
too trivial the task the task is to get
proper training in self transcendence
this is again one of the reasons why I
am opposed to the indiscriminate use of
psychedelics to provoke self
transcendence again I argue against
prohibition but the indiscriminate use
does not give people training in the
discernment to pull apart the self
transcendence that would lead into all
and wonder and the soft transcendence
that can lead into absurdity or horror
so that's why it's very important that
that that the cultivation of self
transcendence always be deeply bound
with the project of enhancing our
capacity for overcoming self-deception
for you know being more wise to put it
in a simple term now I think what we can
do is we can respond to the threat of
absurdity and I'm going to do this in
not this week's video but next week's
video so just briefly there's there are
there are ways of playing with the view
from above playing with this self
transcendence and that don't trigger
absurdity they can afford the
transcendence but constrain it in a way
so that we don't fall prey to absurdity
and this has to do with the fact that
attention and I tried to give you many
examples is simultaneously bottom-up and
top-down and simultaneously flowing in
and out it's a tremendously complex
dynamic self-organization and so there's
a notion you can see and you can see it
both in Spinoza I would argue and other
people in the West and also in in
Buddhist practices so Spinoza gives the
the example of your reading his work the
ethics and you're following all the
premises it's very hard and that but at
some point you can get an awareness of
the argument as a whole and then what
can happen and you can get to a state
that he calls but scan co2 atiba you
sort of get the argument as a whole but
you get how the argument plays in each
premise and you see how each premise
fits into the whole argument it's very
much like I've shown you how you see the
whole word in order to distinguish the
letters but by distinguishing the
letters you are able to write Gestalt
and integrate the whole word and so
you're simultaneously seeing the Gestalt
in the parts and the parts in the
Gestalt
and what that does is that gives you the
access to the range of the
self-transcendence well also getting the
various levels to be deeply
interpenetrating so that there is no
prospective of clash between them and I
would argue and I ask for your
indulgence and wait to see the longer
argument that that's the primary way in
which we respond to absurdity because
there is no argumentation that it's
driving absurdity the arguments are
always after the fact what we need is a
prospective and ultimately participatory
transformation that alleviates our
absurdity and we can see examples of
that
like from completely independent
traditions converging on this stay the
same state that sorry converging on the
same conclusion that there's a state
possible to us that can become more and
more second nature to us in which the
field of self transcendence is opened up
for us but we are not torn asunder by
its polar distance so I think that would
be my attempt and like I say there's
more on this forthcoming in this series
so I hope what I've said here gives you
at least an initial understanding and
that the further working in the episodes
that are pretty like I think the next
one and the one they're after
will give us what we what we need to
carry out I'm sorry it's not give us
well maybe I said give you what you need
and and so that this your understanding
can be improved or at least afforded so
I hope I I hope what we've done together
is we've built a little bit more
understanding are you familiar with the
work of cognitive scientist Donald
Hoffman if so I'm curious to know your
thoughts into his multimodal user
interface theory he seems to be
suggesting a scientific mathematical
proof via evolutionary game theory that
we exist in a sense in Plato's cave a
world of illusion and that's when the
patreon
vrl so so I want to I want to give a
very serious caveat on my response I
basically only I've watched one video by
Hoffman and one argument so I'm gonna
respond on the on the understanding a
social contract here and now that my
understanding it is limited so I'm gonna
respond to the argument I saw and here's
the problem I have with the argument the
argument seems to run off and see this
this goes to I think the words essential
issue the the the central issue is that
realness is a comparative term something
you can only determine if something is
real right in conflict so in contrast to
how an illusion has been overcome
reality is always a comparative term
this is more real than that because I I
I can see from here how I was limited or
self-deceived there now of course that
means I precisely not seeing here how
I'm self deceived or limited I have to
move here and so on and so forth and of
course that means we can never be
completely free from self-deception
because that would mean we'd have to
leap out of our capacity for framing
which I think would be complete
cognitive suicide so let's take that
realness is a comparative term and I
think that's actually operational in
Hoffman's argument he takes it as real
that the evolution has occurred
he takes it as real that certain
scientific measurements have given us
access to the causal and historical
patterns of the world if you're saying
on the basis of how evolution operates I
conclude that we are all in an illusion
I want to know why you think your
information about evolution is not just
itself the losery
if I if I was in a dream if I was in the
matrix in the matrix feeding me all of
this data within my labs or in my
archeological investigations about
biology and evolution that would also be
illusory see the thing is it makes no
sense to me for the reasons I'm trying
to articulate that we could be
comprehensively in an illusion because
there's nothing on the basis of there's
nothing forming the basis of the
comparison now might what he might be
saying is well a lot of our experience
is illusory that's and then yeah that's
great and then it's like not my answer
to that is yeah we sort of have known
that since the axial revolution that a
lot of our experiences losery so the
problem I seem to have with his argument
is it seems to equivocate it does what's
you know kind of maybe a DVD or a
motte-and-bailey kind of thing it seems
to equivocate from something that is
trivial in the sense that we have known
it for a very long time to be true which
is much much of our experience much of
our conceptions are illusory with which
like I said we we've thought this
comprehensively right since the Axio
revolution with a radical claim which is
you know it's all an illusion what and
that's just I think when you make that
claim you just drop down a Cartesian
well and with David Hume in which the
the only thing that's not an illusion is
what's happening right now
solipsistic we isolated in your present
experience because everything else is
inferred
and if that machinery is ultimately a
loser in nature any inference even that
something happened five seconds ago
becomes right open to being open to the
accusation of being a loser so I
wouldn't need to know on how he's using
I need to know more and I copy added
this by saying I only watched the one
thing saw the one argument it wasn't a
short video there was I think was an
hour long but that is it you know that's
not the man's entire body of work and so
I'm acknowledging right now that I might
be unfair to him but insofar as I've
seen people talking about the argument
and the way the the patreon asked me the
question but this is right the if we you
know not only is it an epistemic thing
like how could how could it possibly all
be an illusion on the basis of what
would we point to like I mean I have to
do it on the basis of X I can point to
this and say that's his illusion but at
everything I point to is an illusion I
don't have the basis for calling
anything else an illusion it's it's
exactly equivalent to saying everything
is real it's exactly equivalent to
saying everything is real because
everything has the same epistemic status
and if I have nothing to contrast it
with there's no difference between
saying everything's an illusion and
everything's real they're both equally I
would say meaningless because you're
misusing terms
it's like saying what's north of the
North Pole also if we're in an illusion
that we have no way of escaping from why
would you care what possible difference
could it make it kit you it is
irrational to devote any attention or
effort to things that can make
absolutely no difference at all to what
you believe what you know what you judge
what you act so I you know I I I'm
afraid I've conveyed something that I
didn't want to which is I may have come
across as a little too harsh
but that's just a because it's not
direct that's what I'm trying to say I'm
very I'm very concerned about really
careful use of real and realness and and
things like that and I guess in the end
here I still side with play-doh right
you only know you're in Plato's cave
because you can leave the cave you can
see the fire it's only when you see the
fire that you realize you were only what
looking at shadows it's only when you
walk up the path and into the broad
daylight do you realize that you were
trapped underground so that's ultimately
my response there I would like to thank
Pete John soft for your continuing
support it's been it's been in a been
amazing and I I mean when one engages in
a project like this one one of course
hopes that it will find purchase that
people will find resonance with it that
it will come to matter to people in a
way that affords them amelioration of
issues or enhancing and moving towards
articulation or or flourishing either
individually or collectively and I
thought that that has actually happened
I mean it's it's gone beyond my hopes it
really matters to me to try and make a
difference to the mini crisis and the
fact that people are wanting to support
that project with their money and other
people with time and talent words are
sort of inadequate here it's it's just
it's tremendously encouraging it's
tremendously empowering it
it motivates me to do more I'm going I'm
in the process of working on on on a
follow up series so I just wanna I just
wanna I just want to say that I want to
remind you all about something I said at
beginning we're opening up some limited
spots on to new tiers which include
access to my time which is becoming
increasingly limited precisely because
this prop this project and the ones that
are forthcoming you know are taking off
and again very grateful for that and
those will be live at the end of the Q&A
so we're going to switch off now in the
last few minutes and switch off of the
patreon questions to some live questions
here's the first one these these more
personal ones are always sort of
intriguing and mysterious to me if you
could have a superpower what would it be
your favorite superhero well I suppose I
mean I'm under a bit of an obligation
here because of Amara's here and he and
I play a role-playing game together in
which we actually assume superpowers so
I guess the most honest answer would be
to talk a little bit about what that
looks like for me so my character
basically is kind of like Yoda he could
do sort of super Taichi and he can feel
like from Taoism he can feel the Chi and
work with it and he uses that generally
as a way of trying to get at the depths
of things and come to a more wise
interaction with the world
well of course along the way doing lots
of what-ho and let's get into action of
all that kind of stuff because they'll
have to roll it as a game so I suppose
in one situation how I would extend my
answer is I would superpowers that sort
of enhanced of the sages that I try to
internalize would be this kind of
superpowers of like to have I'd like to
have like I said
like you know that the capacity with Chi
that I see in the Taoist masters I would
to have Socrates's capacity for dialogue
and dialectic and self transcendence and
the integration of rationality and
spirituality and existential involvement
and concern to have that that I mean
it's practically a superpower
even in him but III would I would dearly
love that to have the capacity now let's
be clear I I mean this respectfully I
hope people are getting this but to have
a capacity like a super human capacity
for a gothic love which was perhaps is
this is this not religious I don't
intend it to be was this perhaps what we
saw in Jesus of mathur's to have that
also because of thinking the tremendous
capacity we make persons as I've tried
to argue with agape so those are those
are the three super powers I'd love to
have that that that that more deep in
measurement of mind and body and
embodied in body brain and world that is
exemplified in the Taoist masters to
have Socrates is mastery of dialogue and
dialectic and again I hope it's not
luckily just to have Jesus capacity for
adopting those would be the superpowers
I would most like to have because the
other one strike me as ones that I would
get bored of within about three or four
days I can cast lightning out of my
fingers okay I do that for a day or two
and then what I'm back to I'm miserable
I don't have meaning I'm not doing well
of my relationships right but this what
the superpowers that I've mentioned
super Qi and super agape and super
dialectic I would be able to cultivate
the best possible life and so that's why
I would want those superpowers I hope
that's a good answer to that question
it's an interest
question it's really thought-provoking
in some ways thank you for that
what are you views on trends and
gentleman meditation the technique not
the business this is from Emilio I don't
know very much about it I I've sat I'd
never practice it I've sat with a couple
of people who have practiced that and
sort of compared notes between of a
Pasadena I know there's been some
research done in terms of depth of
meditation some of it good some of it's
suspicious because it's by the
Transcendental Meditation Institute so
conflict of interest bias so I suspect
that so again mostly ignorant I don't
I'm not claiming expertise from the
conversations I had what I see
operational Transcendental Meditation
seems to have important aspects with
deeper forms of a pasta when you you are
you're trying to move into a state of
non-duality like so you get beyond
focusing on the breath and then you
start to focus on the space between the
thoughts and then you write you have the
experience where your attention is
simultaneously as out as it can be in to
the world and as in as it can be into
yourself or soul or psyche and it seems
to me that trends another meditation is
is is trying to get to that place to
that's I think what transcendental
consciousness says I don't know so
that's my best take on it what I would
say of it as not as a practitioner as a
scientist that like I said I'm
suspicious of quite a bit of the studies
because of their biased nature of the
studies I suspected that where
Transcendental Meditation is tapping
into a lot of the attentional processes
that have been studied in other forms of
mindfulness that it's reasonable to
conclude that a TM would have
significant predictive benefits have you
considered a state a series on Plato's
dialogues ha ha ha that's a great
question because the series that I'm
working on now is going to go - it's
going to be about
it's gonna be about Socratic dialogue
we're going to talk about the Platonic
dollar what I'm interested in is the
following I'm interested I had an
amazing conversation I expect everyone
with Jordan Hall would be which or no
but he proposed that what he's talking
about is that the need for a meta
psychic technology by which we Shepherd
the ecology of practices and I thought
that was a really powerful and
interesting thing to say he's also
talked about a bit recently with Tim a
dilemma in boys club if you want to take
a look at a recent video about that
and it struck me that something that did
that in the ancient world was platonic
dialectic now laconic dialectic of
course was a historical thing it was
changing but the you give this constant
reference especially in the neo platonic
tradition that but even with the
platonic tradition right of dialectic as
this practice right that it governs all
of the other spiritual exercises and
regulates them in some important way
Sheppard's them as I try to say picking
up on the ecological metaphor if you'll
allow me and so I'm really interested in
trying to understand what that was and
how it worked and there's just some
great work by Dru Highland and Gonzales
and I'll ball wrap a and a whole bunch
of other people right who are really
unpacking what was going on in the
dialogues and we have to pay attention
to the drama in the dialogue because the
perspectival
and participatory knowing is as
important as the propositions that are
being uttered so all of that I want to
unpack that deeply but then what I want
to do and and this is intended I want to
put that into dialogue with all a lot of
the current practices that people are
engaging in like Dyson starts circling
and some of the work that Peter Lim Barr
Limburg it's doing with you know the
anti debate on authentic relating it's
because we have a rich here we can look
at Socrates and then we can look at the
legacy we can look at the Stoics and we
can look at the way dialectic developed
and changed and then we can put it into
dialogue
with a lot of these current practices
and so that we can hopefully in that
dialogue find a way to tap into the
collective intelligence of a distributed
cognition so that we can get this meta
psycho technology that will allow us to
better cultivate and coordinate a an
ecology of practices and so this this
series is going to be called after
Socrates the pursuit of wisdom through
authentic dialog and so we are going to
be in that series going into the
Platonic dialogues at least for the
first chunk of the series to get a
deeper understanding of what's or attic
and Linkous platonic dialogue mean so
and then again like trace it out and
some of the legacies that come out of it
you know we go the Stoics you know other
other versions of the dialectic and then
put that into dialogue with what's going
on right now as a way of trying to give
us an enriched vocabulary an increased
sense of you know preset a repertoire of
templates so sort of more theoretical
space grammar to move around in as we
try to come up with sets of you know
ways of cultivating ecologies of
practices in a collective and manner
that taps into the power of distributed
cognition so that we can more readily
address the meaning crisis so that was a
great question thank you for asking it
it gave me a chance to plug what's
coming I'm very excited about this this
next series it won't be as long as
awakening from the meeting crisis
probably only be like 20 episodes but
this this issue about how do we get how
do we recover dialogue and dialectic how
do we get at this ability to tap into
both our right destroy the power of our
distributed cognition and the
inexhaustible
the of intelligibility is something that
is crucial and urgent for us right now
and so I want to pick that up in the
next series so and I'm already working
on it I'm doing it and I'm really
looking forward to sharing that with you
and I hope that many of you will find it
beneficial so I think that's it again
I can't get to everybody and I wish I
could I really do actually but I want to
thank you for your time
and we'll be doing these live Q&A every
month on the third Friday of the month
we've sort of settled into a regular
routine and I look forward to seeing you
again in a month from now thank you very
much everyone for your time attention